<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>C on Sakis Kasampalis - Personal homepage</title>
    <link>https://sakisk.me/tags/c/</link>
    <description>Recent content in C on Sakis Kasampalis - Personal homepage</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2012 20:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sakisk.me/tags/c/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>9series: Introduction and chmod</title>
      <link>https://sakisk.me/blog/2012-01-29-9series-introduction-and-chmod/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2012 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sakisk.me/blog/2012-01-29-9series-introduction-and-chmod/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div dir=&#34;ltr&#34; style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; trbidi=&#34;on&#34;&gt;&lt;h3 class=&#34;documentDescription&#34; style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;                            &lt;span class=&#34; kssattr-atfieldname-description kssattr-templateId-widgets/textarea kssattr-macro-textarea-field-view inlineEditable&#34; id=&#34;parent-fieldname-description&#34;&gt;            Introduction to Plan 9 and writing a simple chmod utility&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34; kssattr-atfieldname-description kssattr-templateId-widgets/textarea kssattr-macro-textarea-field-view inlineEditable&#34; id=&#34;parent-fieldname-description&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;I decided to write down some notes about my experiences while playing with &lt;a class=&#34;external-link&#34; href=&#34;http://plan9.bell-labs.com/plan9/&#34;&gt;Plan 9&lt;/a&gt;.  Plan 9 is a free software (OSI certified) distributed operating system  developed in a place that I would like to visit someday: Bell Labs.  Many great programmers have contributed to Plan 9. Among them are the  well-known from the UNIX world Ken Thompson and Rob Pike. Yet another  respected programming figure, Brian Kernighan, claims to be just a &lt;a class=&#34;external-link&#34; href=&#34;http://doc.cat-v.org/plan_9/2nd_edition/README&#34;&gt;casual user&lt;/a&gt; of the system (or at least he did in 1995).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are many novel ideas behind Plan 9. Some of them have already been reimplemented in other operating systems: The &lt;code&gt;/proc&lt;/code&gt; and other in memory pseudo file systems, private group per user, native  UTF-8 support, append-only file permissions, and treating FTP  directories as local. But there are some Plan 9 features that are simply  impossible to implement in the rest systems; or if they are implemented  it is done in a very ugly/hacky way, because their design is not  flexible enough. To mention a few: Namespaces, no need for  root/superuser or &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;-like hacks, every compilation is by default a cross compilation, device files are controlled using clear-text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;      Coding in Plan 9&lt;/h3&gt;Although Plan 9 provides an ANSI/POSIX compatibility layer (APE), it  doesn&#39;t make sense to use it for other than porting purposes.The native C  API of Plan 9 is neither POSIX nor ANSI compatible, but IMHO it&#39;s  cleaner and simpler to use. As an example, let&#39;s look into the  implementation of a simplified &lt;code&gt;chmod&lt;/code&gt; utility.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/1699511.js?file=mychmod.c&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A few comments about the interesting parts of the code. Plan 9 has  simple built-in support for handling command line arguments using the &lt;code&gt;ARGBEGIN/ARGEND&lt;/code&gt; block. &lt;code&gt;argv0&lt;/code&gt; is a convenient name that can be used for referring to the name of the  executable. Applying a new permission mask to a file in Plan 9 is just a  matter of updating the mode flag of the file&#39;s &lt;code&gt;Dir&lt;/code&gt; structure. The result is a nice utility using only a few lines of code. Here&#39;s how it can be used:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;separator&#34; style=&#34;clear: both; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-JqcOHepwI9U/T7_j5P0hrjI/AAAAAAAAAAg/bacxP26KyXk/s1600/9chmod.png&#34; imageanchor=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; height=&#34;97&#34; src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-JqcOHepwI9U/T7_j5P0hrjI/AAAAAAAAAAg/bacxP26KyXk/s400/9chmod.png&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And that concludes this brief introduction to Plan 9. Until next time... Happy Coding!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;      References&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Rob Pike, Dave Presotto, et al. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external-link&#34; href=&#34;http://plan9.bell-labs.com/sys/doc/9.html&#34;&gt;Plan 9 From Bell Labs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Francisco J Ballesteros.&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a class=&#34;external-link&#34; href=&#34;http://lsub.org/who/nemo/9.intro.pdf&#34;&gt;Introduction to Operating System Abstractions using Plan 9 from Bell Labs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;documentDescription&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
